♪
[ÖGEDEI]
Thanks to your lovely earrings,
I have learned that all
is functioning as it should.
[Möge breathes softly]
[ÖGEDEI]
I have to wonder, though...
Will people come
to see it my way
after we have defeated
all the Jin?
[MÖGE] Honestly, I don't have
any idea what he's thinking.
Hm?
[gasps] The slave girl's gone?
Ah!
[exclaims]
Ugh, did she get lost again?
Lady Möge!
[♪ opening theme song playing]
JAADUGAR
[Qadaq grunts]
-Hey, Fatima.
-[Sitara gasps, sighs]
-So this is where you were.
-[gasps softly]
-How dare you run away!
-[Sitara squeals]
Qadaq! You have to help me.
[BOTH] Lord Chinqai?
You can write in Uyghur, right?
[both gasp]
♪
[MAN]
Take care of these as well.
Uh... there's no end in sight.
I'm sorry about this.
Every item
the Great Kha'an purchased
has to be recorded
in our registers.
So why am I here?
Isn't this considered
a man's job?
Just be quiet and get to work.
Many Mongols have never
really had a strong affinity
for reading and writing.
Thus we're short on scribes.
[Sitara gasps] Books!
[both laugh]
Who'll even read these?
This one is by Jabir ibn Hayyan.
-Huh?
-Uh... Oh, nothing.
♪
[Sitara gasps]
Mistress, why is this book
hidden away among the others?
Oh, you have quite a keen eye.
This one's by Jabir.
He lived in Tus long ago.
But I'm afraid it's not
the most reputable of tomes.
What's the subject of his book?
[chuckles] It's alchemy.
[Sitara gasps]
What's that about?
[SITARA]
It details how one can heat
and mix various substances,
such as minerals,
to prepare...
an al-iksir.
An "al-iksir"?
And what is that?
It's a kind of cure-all,
at least I think
that's what it is.
I'm not quite sure.
-[MÖGE] A cure-all?
-[ALL] Huh?
[SITARA] Lady Möge!
Do you mean a medicine
that can cure any ailment?
[Sitara whimpers]
Huh?
[TÖREGENE] This is Fatima.
She is one
of my most faithful attendants,
Boraqchin Khatun.
[SITARA]
So this is the chief empress
of the Mongol Empire...
The Great Khatun.
Why have I been brought out here
to meet her like this?
Listen, Boraqchin,
this girl here says
that she is able
to concoct a cure-all.
A danyao?
Huh?
I, uh... I'm sorry, but I'm
not sure what this is about,
because all I said
is that I'm able to read books
written in Arabic.
-[MÖGE] You what?
-Möge.
[MÖGE] Uh, but...
-That is all. Take your leave.
-[Möge groans]
[BORAQCHIN]
Sorry for making you come here.
[sheep bleating]
So what was all of that about?
Who knows?
-[MÖGE] Hold on!
-[BOTH] Uh?
[SITARA] Lady Möge?
[MÖGE] Say, there's something
I wanted to discuss with you.
The whole reason I asked you
to come out here. [sighs]
Please leave us.
[birds chirping]
[MÖGE] Someone's been
administering poison
-to Boraqchin.
-[Sitara gasps]
[MÖGE] You could see
how emaciated she was,
and all the sores
all over her skin.
Who did this?
Why would they do such a thing?
[MÖGE] I'm not certain,
and I can't prove it.
But I think the culprit
is Boraqchin's physician.
Some time ago,
the Daoists engaged
in a sacred tradition
known as waidan.
What's waidan?
[PHYSICIAN] By combining
the likes of sulfur,
quicksilver, and sandarac,
an elixir called
"danyao" can be created.
It was believed
that after ingesting danyao,
one's body would transform
and become immortal like gold.
Was it really true?
Sadly, no.
Many of the ingredients
were highly poisonous,
shortening the lives
of all who used it.
For that reason,
this archaic practice
was abandoned centuries ago.
He said poison.
I'm sure that's the word
I heard him utter.
Unfortunately,
it isn't much to go on.
If it worries you so,
simply keep the physician away.
As Great Khatun,
surely it would be simple
to replace him.
Töregene.
[TÖREGENE]
Let us return, Fatima.
[SITARA] Um, right.
[exhales softly]
[insects trilling]
[TÖREGENE] Neither one of us
should get involved
with such an eerie woman.
[sighs deeply] How harrowing.
This was the first time
I'd seen the Great Khatun,
and I couldn't help noticing
she's considerably older
than Emperor Ögedei.
You're right. She used
to be his stepmother.
Huh?
[TÖREGENE] Years ago,
Boraqchin and Möge
were married to Genghis Khan,
then Ögedei inherited them
as wives.
[Sitara gasps]
So the two of them
have known each other
for quite a long time then.
When the father dies,
all his wives go to his son,
except for the birth mother.
It's a common arrangement here.
[Töregene sighs]
Boraqchin...
[coughing]
[TÖREGENE] She has no sons,
and she doesn't come
from a large family.
Truth be told,
I don't have any idea
how she became Great Khatun.
[PHYSICIAN] It was believed
that after ingesting danyao,
one's body would transform
and become immortal like gold.
That sounds
exactly like alchemy.
Who knew they had
something so similar
in the east?
An immortal body.
A danyao?
[Sitara gasps]
I wonder if it's... an al-iksir.
The ingredients
are quicksilver, sulfur...
And what were
the other substances again?
[rustling]
-[SITARA] Lady Töregene.
-Huh?
Once more, let's go meet
with the Great Khatun.
Huh? Why is that?
[Sitara chuckles softly]
[Töregene grunts]
You have something
in mind, don't you?
Mm-hmm.
I'd like you
to lend me your power.
Please, Lady Töregene.
[birds chirping]
[SITARA] Al-iksir.
It's a remedy
that renders one immortal.
For generations now,
it's lain at the very heart
of Persian alchemy.
-[Möge gasps]
-[SITARA] Of course,
I cannot prepare
such a thing by myself.
That said, if you were to
assist me, Great Khatun,
I could.
Why is there talk of this again?
Because I believe
it's you who's been seeking it.
Am I wrong?
[Boraqchin grunts]
Wait. Is that really true?
From the moment I laid eyes
on you,
there was something
that struck me.
If I may surmise,
based on your appearance...
Have you been ingesting
rahj al-gar by any chance?
[MÖGE] What's rahj al-gar?
[SITARA] It's a red stone
that can be found
in volcanoes.
And in the east,
I've been told they refer to it
as "sandarac."
[Boraqchin gasps]
So I was right.
In al-iksir and danyao,
rahj al-gar is regarded
as an essential ingredient,
after all.
According
to the ancient physician
named Hippocrates,
rahj al-gar does have
medicinal effects
in small doses.
Although, it's poisonous
with continued use,
causing loss of appetite,
lesions on the skin,
and the growth of tumors,
which is what you
seem to be suffering from.
So my fear that you were
slowly being poisoned
is completely unfounded,
and you chose
to ingest it yourself?
Goodness, Möge.
Is that honestly
what you were thinking?
Fatima, right?
You should take a look inside
the drawers on that shelf.
There's the rahj al-gar.
Why were you taking
such a harmful thing?
[Boraqchin sighs]
To become immortal. Was that it?
[Boraqchin grunts]
[MÖGE] Huh?
Yes, that's right.
I'm not a young woman anymore.
I'd like to live a long life.
Mistress Boraqchin.
[SITARA] If you wouldn't mind,
please ingest this.
Its medicine will cure you.
[ALL] Huh?
[breathes softly]
Tell me, what is this?
-A Jada stone.
-Jada stone?
I thought you were not supposed
to ingest Jada stones.
You're wrong. It's called
a bezoar stone in Persia,
where it has been recognized
as an antidote.
I assume you haven't put a curse
on this, right?
Is this the face of someone
who wishes you ill?
[Töregene groans]
[BORAQCHIN] Hm.
[Boraqchin coughs]
After you've recovered
and are feeling better,
please summon us here again.
We'll talk more
of the al-iksir, if you wish.
[SITARA]
Thank you very much.
[TÖREGENE]
But I haven't done anything.
[SITARA] Of course you have.
If you hadn't been able to find
those Persian physicians
who spoke with us,
I never would have learned
about the rahj al-gar.
[TÖREGENE]
What'll you do about Chagatai?
[SITARA] I think we may
have been rushing things
by assuming we should
approach him right away.
At this point,
by just focusing on earning
the Great Khatun's trust,
a path will reveal itself.
One for us both, I hope.
Yes.
Absolutely.
SUMMER, A.D. 1230
[SITARA (ADULT)]
Shortly thereafter,
the Mongol Emperor
embarked on an expedition
against the Jin dynasty.
SHANXI REGION - HOUSE OF ÖGEDEI
FRONT-LINE CAMP
You can put those
right over there for now.
-[BORAQCHIN] Möge.
-[both gasp]
[MÖGE] Boraqchin!
-[Kirgistani exclaims]
-You're well enough
to be walking outside?
[chuckles]
-Yes, so it seems.
-[Kirgistani exclaims]
-It's all thanks to Fatima.
-Yeah!
[BORAQCHIN] Indeed.
[ATTENDANT] I have a message
from Empress Boraqchin.
She's requested that Miss Fatima
come speak with her again.
[Sitara grunts]
[Töregene exhales]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
The following year...
MONGOLS - SOUTHERN SONG
KAIFENG JIN DYNASTY
to ensure
the Jin capital of Kaifeng
would be
completely surrounded,
Tolui's army sought permission
to pass through the lands
of the Southern Song.
But instead...
They killed our messenger?
So that's the Southern Song's
response.
Should we all turn back?
Hardly.
We'll proceed south
exactly as we planned.
We've already received
their unfavorable reply.
If we go, none of their people
will take this quietly.
[Tolui scoffs] Well...
we'll just have
to defeat them too.
[soldiers shouting]
[groans]
[all grunting]
[SITARA (ADULT)] Tolui's army
breached the fortified pass,
then continued along
the mountain roads.
[TOLUI] These mountains prove
to be no match for us after all.
The Great Kha'an
will be most pleased.
Huh?
Without question.
I have no doubt my brother
will be overjoyed!
[laughs]
[sheep bleating]
[SORGHAGHTANI] Dear God,
please bless Tolui
and watch over him.
[HULEGU] Come now, you know
Father would never lose.
TOLUI'S SON
HULEGU
Why even bother praying for him?
My! How could you say that
before God?
I feel confident
that my dear husband
would never lose in battle.
That said,
misfortune can strike
outside of the battlefield.
Those with too much power
are viewed with great fear
and resentment.
Mother, then you
must be careful too.
I must be? [giggles]
No one would give me
any thought whatsoever.
[HULEGU] I can only hope so.
[sheep bleating]
♪
[Sitara grunts]
[bells jingle]
Here you are. [grunts]
Thank you. Right there is fine.
♪
There, fresh off the pot.
Thank you very much.
I thought I'd bring you
some urum, Lady Töregene.
[exclaims]
I love it the most now
when it's at its ripest.
[chuckles]
So good.
Autumn will soon be upon us,
and the urum will be used
to make butter.
This may be the last batch
of the season.
You should have some as well.
Oh, I couldn't.
Besides, Empress Boraqchin
has just asked to speak with me.
What, again?
I'm sorry.
I should be going now.
[Töregene sighs]
♪
That's all right by me.
[SITARA]
In the natural world,
substance and qualities
are very closely intermingled.
By altering
its essential properties,
one thing can be entirely
transformed into another.
In much simpler terms,
that is what this treatise
by Jabir is really all about.
What does it mean?
[BORAQCHIN] By understanding
an object's qualities,
one can make whatever
is desired,
whether that be a remedy
or a weapon.
Oh, wow, amazing!
Just look at sandarac.
When rahj al-gar is heated,
it immediately turns white
and becomes more toxic.
They seem to have approached
the truth of this world,
both, the scholars
of your homeland,
and Daoists
of the Middle Kingdom.
[Sitara gasps]
[SITARA] The Great Kha'an
and Empress Boraqchin,
they're thinking about
what happens
after the Jin
have been conquered.
And they're taking
a broader view of the world.
Uh...
[Sitara sighs]
What's the matter?
Are you all right?
[SITARA] Uh, well,
Lord Chinqai mentioned
that he was struggling
with the shortage
of scribes here.
But I don't understand
how that could be.
Haven't the Mongols
obtained people and knowledge
from all over the world?
-[BORAQCHIN] Mm.
-[MÖGE] Hm?
The Mongols
have obtained intellectuals,
but a great vast majority
of them...
fall under
the House of Tolui's rule now.
[Sitara gasps]
Just like the military,
Prince Tolui is entitled
as Otchigin.
If that's true,
then couldn't the Great Kha'an
just use his authority?
Are you suggesting
that he should pilfer
his own brother's property?
I... I am sorry.
There's an intellectual
imbalance as well?
Actually, that should work
to our advantage.
Do you truly believe
that would be for the best?
[BOTH] Huh?
[SITARA]
I can't help but feel afraid.
The House of Tolui controls
military and intellectual might.
Well, that only means...
...that it is
even more important
to work in tandem with them.
[chuckles]
Does Prince Tolui
feel the same way, though?
[MÖGE] Hmm.
[BORAQCHIN] Möge, forgive me,
but could you leave us?
[gasps softly]
Till Möge brought you to us,
I have no recollection
of ever once
having seen you here before.
So who in the world are you?
[SITARA] I'm sure you wouldn't
be familiar with me.
After all, I was serving
as Princess Sorghaghtani's aide.
I urge you to be cautious.
She hasn't given up
on her ambition...
to see Prince Tolui
become the Great Kha'an
and for herself
to be the Great Khatun.
[Boraqchin gasps]
Sorghaghtani, you say?
I see. I shall bear it
in mind then.
But why have you suddenly chosen
to divulge all this
to me, Fatima?
I must warn you
to choose your answer wisely.
[SITARA] It's all right.
I can do this.
As of now,
I have a fairly good sense
of what's going on in her mind.
Truth be told,
I don't have any idea
how she became Great Khatun.
[SITARA] No matter how wise
this woman is,
there must be many who think
as Lady Töregene does.
People question how she came
to hold such authority,
which is why she clings
so firmly to her own acumen.
Simply put,
you and Emperor Ögedei
have filled me
with a sense of hope!
[Boraqchin exclaims]
[SITARA] The great wisdom
you both display
makes you worthy of ruling
this world with honor and grace.
Yes.
♪
[Boraqchin gasps]
Do you really think so?
Of course I do.
[footsteps]
[SITARA] I expected her
to be a fairly crafty one,
but she was so easy to handle.
I have to tell Lady Töregene
about this.
-[FEMALE SLAVE] Excuse me!
-Uh?
[pants] Um, I was attempting
to make butter,
but I'm still not used to it,
and I have plenty of milk.
You see, it's over there.
I'd be glad to help.
Don't worry.
[exclaims]
Thank you so very much.
[female slave chuckles]
Oh, Lady Töregene.
Guess it can wait.
[footsteps]
[SITARA] Lady Töregene?
[BORAQCHIN]
There's no need for you
to feel so nervous.
I just have something I wanted
to discuss with you.
GREAT KHATUN BORAQCHIN
[♪ closing theme song playing]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
Next time. "Tengri."
TENGRI